<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A serious aviso to the good people of this nation, concerning that sort of men, called Levellers. / By J. Philolaus.</title>
            <author>Philolaus, J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92935</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872905</idno>
  <idno type="VID">165116</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240945857</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E555_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5827</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872905</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99872905e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E555[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A serious aviso to the good people of this nation, concerning that sort of men, called Levellers. / By J. Philolaus.</title>
                  <author>Philolaus, J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Cole, at the sign of the Printing-Press in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J. Philolaus is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Levellers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165116:1"/>
            <p>A Serious Aviso TO THE GOOD PEOPLE OF THIS NATION, Concerning that Sort of Men, called Levellers.</p>
            <p>By J. PHILOLAUS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Juven.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Evertere domos totas aptantibus ipsis dii facilis.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Peter Cole,</hi> at the Sign of the Printing-Press in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:165116:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165116:2"/>
            <head>A SERIOVS AVISO TO THE LEVELLERS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear fellow Citizens,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I consider the strange dispensations of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence upon us of this Nation, I cannot but be swallowed up in admiration and deepest ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, how it hath been pleased to scourge us but with light afflictions, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding blesse us with such transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent mercies as we should hardly have dar'd to have wish'd, though had we been after his own heart, nay the apple of his eye. <hi>Germany</hi> hath been drown'd in a sea of blood, or wasted by fury of the fire, yet still how far off asserting a true Liberty and Reformation? <hi>France</hi> notwithstanding she hath dar'd bravely, stil groans under her burdens (&amp; which is her grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test burden) is forc'd to fawn upon a distrustful Tyrant. But we among whom for almost a decad of years there hath been a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual effusion of blood, know neither Rapes, nor Desolations, nay are ignorant almost of the common calamities of war, while we have puld down those powers of the Earth that stood between us and our Felecity, and have rendred our selves a people abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Free, with lesse bloodshed, and in less time than our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors have often and more laboriously and miserably spent in obtaining some specious shadow of freedom as a gift and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence of some unworthy Usurper, or else in maintaining of some unjust Title in order to the lust and vile ambition of some insatiate Pretender.</p>
            <p>When (I say) I revolu these things with my self (as truly I do often with a great deal of religious astonishment) I instantly think that there is more in this than the hand of Man; nay that the hand of the Almighty Himself hath visibly appeared: And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165116:3"/>since when he Appears none may Resist; I cannot but account it an ungrateful stiff-neckedness in any who shall not calmly close with all these mercies, and willingly resign himself up into the power which hath miraculously snach't us from the snares of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, and vigorously protected us in the full restoration of our Liberties.</p>
            <p>Now since the Parliament, that now sits, hath been the great Instrument of all this: As I have never yet been awanting faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully both to serve and honor them; so have I had too many oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions of pitty and sorrow in their behalf, especially since having from the beginning strugled both with such <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>outward</hi> Resistances, and patiently suffered under such furious Invectives, Rash Engagements, as might well nigh deter the most Resolute vertue from persisting its purposes: they should in the very End, when they were about to reap the Fruits of their Constancy and Integrety be thus afresh assaulted, and that by a sort of people sprung out of their own Bowels, dissenting from their own En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and Actuating their Resolutions with greater fury (and possibly worse Consequences) than could be expected from the Malice and Rancor of these very enemies, whose Principals and Interests are diametrically opposite.</p>
            <p>'Tis of these people (beloved countrymen) that I would at this time (amidst hast and distractions) bid you forbear, &amp; conjure by all your late sufferings, present quiet, &amp; future expectations, to dis-favor and dis-beleeve; for as Divines say, those Errors are the most pernicious that keep neerest distance from the Truth; so in Politicks, these Factions are the most dangerous that seem to comply the most with the truest and direct interest in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weal. For walking in the disguise either of Justice or truth they are both more strong and unseen, and yet they can (in due time, setch out of their own principles, pretences enough for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication and wickednesse.</p>
            <p>This sort of men who (like other factions, content in time to own those Names which the scorn of others first puts upon them) are called <hi>Levellers,</hi> were at first mingled with the best Patriats, and Assertors of our Freedom, that if they themselves had not violently burst forth, there had never been known a separation, but they had equally with them shar'd the glory of our Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and never been noted Common disturbers; But now since
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165116:3"/>by such a disorderly avulsion they have made themselves another body and are either pleased to Fancy or Attempt great things; let us take the pains to examine the base whereon they now stand, and see whether al these gorgeous pretences and splended Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentations wil not quickly vanish into Specters and Chymaeras.</p>
            <p>And first for the <hi>Persons:</hi> wherein we may consider 2. things. First, whether they are <hi>fit</hi> to do it. Or Secondly, whether they <hi>ought</hi> to do it. For fitness there needs not much be said concerning the Persons, who are all of them private men, utterly unverst in Government, and some of them of boisterous and turbulent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that would possibly Recoyle at their own Designations if they were once setled. Now how fit any man is to direct and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign in any thing wherein through long and constant observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he cannot pretend to a piercing judgment and perfect insight, let any man judg: But how much of al affairs and observations, those which concern the Republick are the Nicest and most en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled? Contingences, fraud of men, succession of time, besides the Narrow poor blindness of mans Reason will evince: and the frequent examples of of Common-wealths (whose laws still nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alteration or explanation) demonstrate, That though it be easie to frame an Idea, and to trick it up with Nice Capriccios and airy whimzies, yet this, if it come to be setled and imposed would drag along with it more inconveniences, than the other if which it discomposed; and therefore I am verily of opinion that Fantastick Eutopian Common wealths (which some witty men, some Philosophers have drawn unto us) introduced among men, would prove far more loathsom &amp; be more fruitful of bad consequences than any of those of the Basest allay yet known, and of this opinion I am the rather, because they seeme all to me rather suited to the private conceptions and humors of their Architects than to the Accommodation and Penefit of Men, and that besides they contain many times, things naturally Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous, there would also appear abundance of Absurdities which only conversation and time could make apparent. Nay, and we see that the divine <hi>Plato</hi> (a man never too much commended for his other writings) yet when he came to handle this subject, has had the Fate to mannage it so, that he has incur'd the censure and exception of a many learned pens.</p>
            <p>Omit al this: since we have not constituted these men our lawgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165116:4"/>&amp; therefore are not implicitly bound to accept what they propose, lets ask them from whence they have this draught, &amp; for what reason they conceive it for to urge it so much to us? if they say they have it by inspiration or Revealation (as I think they wil not) we shal begin to suspect black fumes of <hi>Hypocondriac</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy or distemper of the Imagination, if they say from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: from whence is it? do the people that live under it live happily by it? or are they sure our clime and humor is fit to receive it? or how came they to offer the imposition, And if the people will not accept it, what then? if they say 'tis that which they conceive most rational and necessary, I ask again whether they have some superiority of reason above other men, if they have, it remains on their side to prove: for we positively deny it, if they have not, their conclusions are but the resultance of so many private votes, For every man that has reason may have free liberty to use it; and then the thing hanging in doubt and suspence, where's the necessity? If they say the thing be so just as that it will force it self unto all mens understandings, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentate them to comply with it, I must demand whether they mean mankind in genral, or us in particular? if the former, alas the customs, and educations, and complexions of some nations are so different that the very reasons differ, and what reason is there they should all walk by one Rule? if the latter, they run but the <hi>Circle</hi> unless they tell us why to us only, and then demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate them useful to us: which if they do, we must again look whether they be such as may be better'd, or no, if they grant they may, then affirm I that he that produces a better plat-form ought out of their own principles (or which is stronger, out of reason) to be receiv'd; and then why urge they this Sceptical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of theirs; if they say it <hi>Cannot:</hi> I must return and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stisie, that No humane government is absolutely perfect, and that particularly there are many things weak and trivial in theirs, and again ask them whether they would have it changable or unchangable, if changable, what need all this stir for a thing of a day, and what necessity is there so to disorder the present frame and make our selves liable to the Designs and Dangers of Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for so smal a thing: if unchangable, Is it perfect? that I think they will not say, if imperfect, how will they offer to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude it upon a people when it may every day grow more and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165116:4"/>more hateful, and restrain them from a freedom of change, and whether were not these provisions of theirs, the Foundations of a most absolute and exact Tyranny.</p>
            <p>For point of duty, since your selves are the most eager for equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of persons, 'tis but just we suppose ye equal to the rest, &amp; if you be equal, I beseech you how came you by the super-intendency, if it be in respect of personal endowments (as I perceive few among ye stars of the first magnitude) this might enable you to advise but not to command, Besides you being willing to melt all this Nation into one body, ye must needs be but such a part of it, and such a number, and can ye shew me why a greater number of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men (and ye are no more) not being Representatives or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates may not lay the same claim to their Moddel, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence bring the <hi>Dagon</hi> of Monarchy once more amongst us, &amp; then have we not labored our selves into a double Tyranny, if they say they do it in Right of the people, I demand how they can shew their Authority from the people: If they say from the law of Nature, the dissenting partyes must be considered, &amp; heard; and who would you have Judges? If they deny the Representative at <hi>Westminster</hi> a Parliament, I must enquire, why they deny it to be one: They will say, it was call'd by the King's Writ, and the King's power determining with his death they ought to dissolve. But then I will ask whether the joynt Consent of the 3. Estates (as they stood) were not more binding than any single Act of the Kings; this I think they deny not: Well, the King and they agree (and it was then adjudged an excellent Act) That they should not dissolve without the consent of all the 3. Estates: Now there being no King to dissolve them, may not we as well affirm that they are indissolvable, nay better; then that they are <hi>de jure</hi> disolv'd already upon the King's death, For when <hi>Two powers are put together, the strongest needs must prevail:</hi> and that power by which they sit being greater than that power by which they should not sit, it follows they ought to sit, and if they sit they are a Parliament, and if a Parliament, why ought a company of private men to stir against them without the penalty of disobeying Parliamentary power: And since the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of private men not derived from their Authority are unva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and illegal, I wonder who can justifie theirs.</p>
            <p>To prove my Assumption, That the Parliament is a Parliament,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165116:5"/>I must destroy that common objection which comes from al sider, That 'tis Imperfect, under Restrant, &amp; mangled of a many Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. For their imperfection, since they exceed Fourty you need not care, and I beleeve not many months since you could have been content they had been a less number; and though in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement</hi> (as you call it) you multiply the diminishing of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to two hundred at least, yet I am confident that if it serve any design of yours, you could easily be content to abate the Rigor of this Rule and shrink into a lesser number: however what Laws they find till they be Repeal'd they must stand by, and you that traffick so much in <hi>Cooks.</hi> Institutes may there find some text to adjudge it, for my part I value the argument of as little force, as the House themselves conceive the restraint to be, which you say lies upon them, for they have declared themselves free from all such kind of fear; if they were guarded any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than for their own necessary defence, 'tis a wonder why their guards remove so oft up and down upon their commands, or why they assert their liberty in not satisfying the souldery point-blank at every humour, although in respect of their signal and faithful services they are desirous to use all indulgence to them, as to that means which under God hath preserved them in that safety and flourishing prosperity wherein they now sit: and for the secluding of the Members, if there were any injury at all, it was to the Gentlemen themselves, and yet what injury it was to put restraint upon them who manifestly violated their trusts and endeavoured to comply with the enemy, ye may judg, it seems ye once had the charity to forgive it, for till ye had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vore'd your selves from us ye were not known to complain of it, but rather (supposing it injust) were content to connive at it so long as it conduc'd to your own ends, and indeed were there nothing in the world to excuse it, The soveraign necessity &amp; high dāger to excuse it were enough, the good party being at that time almost overborn into an unworthy conclusion of an injust Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and we ready to receive again the Basilisk into our armes, But how you can urge or demonstrate any such danger seems impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me especially concurring with so benign a Parliament who hasten with that slowness which is but requisite to justice to make a full accomplish for all your desires so far as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the happiness of the people whom they represent and do
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165116:5"/>not go <hi>beyond the Altar,</hi> withal the army were in a publick capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, cemented and engaged by a many declarations, owned by several endearments of the Parliament: and crowned by a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of noble victories, whereas you being a dis-joynted sort only of private men lie not under any such capacity nor cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then by wishes or propositions intermeddle (as I told you) with any thing of publick concernment and therefore I hope I may from the resultance of what hath been said, affirm, <hi>That this Parliament are at this time the sole Trustees of the Republick that the same penalties ought to fall upon them who actually disobey them, as upon those who violate the majesty of a people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I am rather encouraged to say this; for suppose that in the late convulsion of government all the existant power what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever had been Null'd or Suspended, yet surely that which first seised of the Rule, or first restor'd it self, was for that time the lawful and only Government; But the Parliaments power was so far from being vacated, that they continued still entire (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less that some putrifi'd limbs were lop't off) and therefore ought still to be obeyed. But put the case (as ye say) that the sword prevail'd only, yet the swords acknowledgment tacitly envested and enabled the Parliament, had it not been able before, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if (as ye lately objected in a Letter to the Lord General) the Army were a distinct interest &amp; combin'd only together with the intent of performing such and such resolutions; Moreover, granting either the Army could confirm the Parliament or were not subordinate, or stood meerly upon their own engagement, yet so long as they persist, having as publick, visible, and possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly good reasons as your propositions, I see not why they being in a publick capacity should not rather be first heard.</p>
            <p>But since the Army are under the pay and service of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let those men that have but been acquainted with the Name or Notions of bare moral honesty be Judges, whether you take a manly or gentile course in effectuating of your desires, in Endeavouring by your Spies and Emissaries to foment jealousies in the Army; debaush the minds of Souldiers, withdraw them from the obedience of their Commanders, and retard our service in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the preservation of which does in our politick interest almost as neer concern as the preservation of our own <hi>Harths</hi> and <hi>Altars:</hi> Is this the way to consumate a many glorious pretences,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165116:6"/>by insinuating into the soldiers spirits arguments of contumacy? For my part I shall ever be jealous of that <hi>good</hi> which is effected by such bad means, and suppose that under the gilded pretences of such as make use of them; there ever lies something both poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonous and formedable.</p>
            <p>For your desires themselves, since the Parliament have prevented you in the modest and reasonable part of them, and are still going forward with pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous provision for settlement, I think they may very wel be excused to decline those parcels of yours which are rash and vile, and truly I think, both parties considered together, that they wil be found the Abler to judg of them: For whereas there is on the one side a many Raw, Inconsiderate, Unexperienc'd young men: There is on the other a many grave and sage persons, long verst in the Arts of Government and humors of the people, whose very Interest oblieges them to justice and a due quietation of the people: For as we are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver like to have again a Representative so throughly purged and winnowed, so shall we never have any one again whose obligations will be so point blank opposite to the adverse party and their head.</p>
            <p>But lest ye object that I fraudulently insist only upon generals, I shal brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch at some of your propositions (for to do it particularly &amp; fully may be a task by it self) and from hence demonstrate, that you only lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a frantick Democracy and vile confusion, I shal not much insist upon that wherein you deny that any Member of Parliament shal be chosen for the next, Because I beleeve it proceeds rather out of malice and untoward pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, than any serious reason or discretion; only I see no reason why those men whose fidelity we have so long and largely tasted (those whose misde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors have ejected them I plead not for) should be debarred from confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming us in our opinions, and assisting us with their Counsels the next time; But this seems strang to me, that if the Parliam, wil not just when you dismiss them dissolve, that you wil be ready with an Anti-Parliament for them, &amp; so dispossess them, yet suppose they were upon such Noble Counsels as you your selves could not really dislike (as no doubt they wil be upon such as good men cannot dislike) would you break the thrid of their Debates, because it was your pleasure as that time? what a violation were it to Justice &amp; Parliament! and what an hiddeous act and example of yours, and how far were the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion from being a Tumult? It were me thinks a very strang thing to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a company of choise Gentlemen, &amp; that in the very midst of their debats, which being of publick relations must be oft Repeated, often discussed, and many to be satisfied, it is not to be supposed, they can have so sudden a determinotion as the Resolutions of a few private men conspiring in a Chamber; But pray let me ask you, suppose you could glean up a Mock-Synod, whether could you hold it lawfull or unlawful? if the first, whether were it actually a Patliament before that other dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved, or not till it were? if it were a true Parliament before the other broke up, then there were two Parliaments together, a thing never dream'd of but at Oxford, and then whether were they both true
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165116:6"/>Parliaments, and whether might they not both vote contrarieties and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions: if not till the Parliament were dissolved, then all the Elections were void, and such a suspension is both against Law, Reason and Example; if it be unlawful, it were but a Seditious sort of people tumultuously ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, and so to be remanded to their own homes: Yet I speak not this any way to maintain a perpetuity in this Parliament, but onely to assert their freedom of sitting and dissolving, free from all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal force and power whatever; and if it be so intirely within them, I see not why they should not choose their own time, both in respect of Right (as I have proved) as in respect of Duty, lest they should leave things imperfect or unsetled, and consequently leave a way for greater Breaches: and that we have some Reason to think thus, is, That they have appointed a day to consider of the choosing of a New Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; and for most of the Gentlemen themselves, they are so oppressed with the continuance and weight of the publique Burthen, that they desire nothing more then to be eased of it.</p>
            <p>Neither do I know whether or no in your Agreement, you give the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple too great a swing, and render their power far more Unlimited and Arbitrary then is even consistent with Democracy it self: For truly, he that considers the giddiness, inconstancy, and sometimes perversness of the Multitude, would be loath that the whole Ruines of Government should be turned into their hands immediately, and that their power should not be somewhat restrained and regulated. From this we read such ridiculous, contradictious and pitiful Changes in the Populacy of <hi>Athens;</hi> and from hence came all those various Disturbances, which for a long time afflicted <hi>Florence:</hi> whereas if it be modestly disposed, and sweetly tempered (as we have reason to hope will be the Resultance of the Councels of the Parliament) it is the best assurance of the happiness of a people, whose Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is not to be valued according to the Extent, but Use and Safety.</p>
            <p>Nor do I think I any way plead the cause of those insatiable Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants the Lawyers, nor yet defend either the Intricacy or Subtilties of the Law it self, if I affirm, That in endeavoring to take away some intangled Knots, and causes of unnecessary Delay, you pluck up the whole Roots of the Law, and render it nothing but a means of speedy Injustice: Not that I could wish any thing preserved in it, that might foment Debates, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a just Cause: But that I know there will be such Contingencies and Perplexities happen in the course of life, that it will be impossible for a Countrey Jury, or some Annual Magistrate, not verst or bred that way, ever to determine.</p>
            <p>Another thing is, That this <hi>Buskin</hi> of yours is fitted to all Interests,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165116:7"/>and ye endeavor to catch all Broken-Parties within the Drag Net of your Interest: yet you may consider, left in case you should prevail, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther those men would not be <hi>Coloquintada</hi> or no in your Broth; the Countreymans Snake (in the Fable) lay as dead in the cold, but once warm, began to hiss and sting: Believe it, if you nourish these Serpents, you may expect no better from them; for who knows not what danges there is in the Reconciliation of a Civil Enemy; and your selves cannot be ignorant, what contrariety your Principles and Interest holds with all the other of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Others I could adde to these, but that I purpose not to swell above my intended Brevity; and I suppose, whoever is really possest about these, may have a shrewd guess at the rest. For my part, whatever Ends drive you on to these courses, whether you occultly act the designs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists, as some such not to say, or that ye are driven on by private Enmity and Animosity, or that you are discontented at the present State, and labor a Change, or that 'tis onely your Indiscretion hurries into all the Tumults, I should earnestly sue unto you, That you would peaceably apply your selves to your several Callings, and not put your Sickle into that Harvest, in which, it seems, Providence hath not appointed you Laborers: but sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down, and expecting the out-going of the Divine Will, you may all in your several stations, enjoy the sweet Comforts of Peace and Blessing promised to peaceable men; and withal, avoid that punishment and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny which must necessarily happen to the Firebrands of a Countrey.</p>
            <p>And for you (my Countreymen) who are not as yet touched with the Venom, I shall onely wish this Paper an Antidote to preserve you, that you may not shut your eyes at the mighty Appearances of Providence, nor turn Renegado's from his Instruments, but quietly awaiting the issue of these things, you may perceive and feel what a blessedness it is, Not to joyn in the Designs of wicked men, who though they may for a while storm and prosper, yet at the length they must be overthrown, and have their faces covered with Shame and Confusion.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>21 <date>11 <hi>Maii,</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>